Finding Aid for Michigan Botanical Club Records, 1941-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Botanical Club Records 1941-2009
Michigan Botanical Club.
6 linear feet
Organization formed in 1941 with the purpose of conserving all plants native to Michigan. The name of the organization was originally the Michigan Wildflower Association. The name was changed in 1949. Series in record group include: History and constitution; Membership records; Minutes; Reports; Newsletters; Financial materials; Correspondence; Chapter records; and Activities files.
9440 Bn 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library on February 5, 2001. Donor no. 8202.
The record group is open for research.
The Michigan Botanical Club was founded on May 31, 1941. It was first named as the Michigan Wildflower Association. The aims of the organization are: (1) conservation of all types of native plants, (2) education of the public to appreciate and preserve plant life, (3) sponsorship of research and publications on the plant life of the State, (4) sponsorship of legislation to promote the preservation of Michigan native flora and to establish suitable sanctuaries and natural areas and (5) cooperation in programs concerned with the wise use and conservation of all natural resources and scenic features.
On June 2, 1946 the name of the organization was changed to Michigan Association for Native Plant Protection. Finally, after some controversy among the members, the name was changed again on February 27, 1949 to the Michigan Botanical Club.
Since the beginning of the organization, the members agreed to encourage the foundation of regional chapters. Soon thereafter, four chapters were formed. The first one was the Bay County Wildflower Association, which was active until 1952. The second chapter formed was the Saginaw Wildflower Society, which consisted of a boy scout group and became inactive during World War II because the members entered military service. The third chapter founded was in Marquette and the other chapter founded was the East Grand Rapids Junior Chapter which lasted until 1948. There was also another chapter founded on 1949, called the Wildlife Chapter. It became inactive in 1951. Now there are five chapters as part of the organization: Huron Valley Chapter, Red Cedar Chapter, Southeastern Chapter, Southwestern Chapter and White Pine Chapter.
Publications have been an important resource for the organization. One of its first publications was a series of bulletins given out by the Southeastern Chapter. Some of the titles were Flowers of Spring, Autumn Colors and Names of Plants among others. With the formation of the Huron Valley Chapter, the idea of publishing a botanical journal was conceived. The result was the publication of The Michigan Botanist, a quarterly journal. This journal stills circulating to the members.
The Michigan Botanical Club also publishes its Special Publication Series. The first booklet was Some Common Mushrooms of Michigan Parks and Recreation Areas, published on 1963. The Club has published other booklets and a member newsletter. It has a web page, http://michbotclub.org.
Another major Club effort is the Big Trees Project. The project started soon after 1941 and its mission is to discover, measure and record Michigan's biggest trees and shrubs. Other activities organized by the Club have been Campouts and the foundation of the Natural Areas Council on 1951.
* The information contained in this note was taken from The Michigan Botanical Club: an Early History, written by Herbert E. Conant in 1984, available on the Club's web site. http://michbotclub.org/earlyhistory
The records of the Michigan Botanical Club, date from 1941 to 1993 and consists of minutes, correspondence, and reports. The files are an important resource not only for understanding the history and achievements of the Club, but also for the study of flora in Michigan. These records are divided into ten series: History and Constitution, Membership, Minutes, Reports, Newsletters, Finances, Correspondence, Chapter Records, Activities and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Michigan Botanical Club.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.
- History and Constitution
  The History and Constitution series contains the article "The Michigan Botanical Club: an Early History" written by Herbert E. Conant in 1984. It also contains records about the Constitution and its proposed amendments during the 1950s and 1960s.
  - History, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Constitution
    - 1955, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1962, 1967 (Box 1)
- Membership
  The Membership series is arranged chronologically and contains membership lists and information from 1947 to 1993. There are also lists from the Officers and Boards of Directors from 1941 to 1961.
  - Officers and Board of Directors, 1941-1963 (Box 1)
  - Membership, 1947-1993 (except 1986-1988), 9 folders (Box 1)
- Minutes
  The Minutes series contains the minutes from the Board of Directors meetings and from the Club general meetings. This series is arranged chronologically and covers the period 1941-1993, and 1998-2005.
  - 1941-1993, 41 folders (Box 1)
  - 1998-2005, 8 folders (Box 6)
- Reports
  The Reports series is divided into six sections arranged alphabetically. This series includes Election Reports from the Nominating Committee that provides an idea of the organization's election process. The Presidents Reports present information about the activities and achievements of the Club during the year. There is also a section about the process of changing the name of the organization to Michigan Botanical Club.
  - Conservation Committee Report, October 22, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Education Committee Report, October 22, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Elections Reports
    - 1944-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970, 1973-1975, 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Name Change Reports 1947, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Native Plant Protection Committee Report, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Presidents Reports
    - 1943-1944, 1947, 1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1967 (except from 1964) (Box 2)
    - 1982, 1985 (Box 2)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series is arranged chronologically and covers the period 1943-2009.
  - 1943, 1946-1949 (except 1948) (Box 2)
  - 1950-1958 (except 1955) (Box 2)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - 1970-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1980-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1990-1993 (except 1992) (Box 2)
  - 1994-2009 (Box 6)
- Finances
  The Finances series is divided into five sections arranged alphabetically. It includes the reports from the Treasurer about income and expenses of the Club each year. Other sections are Federal Income Tax Reports and State Non-Profit Corporation Reports.
  - Form 990-Federal Income Tax (Box 2)
    - 1944-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (except 1966) (Box 2)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Cash Fund Accounts, 1980-1985 (except 1981) (Box 2)
  - State Non-Profit Corporation Reports
    - 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (except 1963) (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Records, 1943-1973 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1951-1959 (except 1953-1954), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1980-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1990-1993 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is arranged chronologically and contains letters sent to and by Board of Directors members. The series covers the period 1944-1988.
  - 1944, 1947 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1959 (except 1951-1953), 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1960-1988 (except 1979-1980), 9 folders (Box 3)
- Chapter Records
  Chapter Records contain documents from active and inactive chapters. This series is arranged alphabetically. This series demonstrates the influence of chapters on the work of the Michigan Botanical Club, since some of the projects and publications of the organization were created by chapters.
  - Bay County Chapter, 1945-1950 (Box 3)
  - Huron Valley Chapter
    - Records 1960-1969 (except 1962-1964) (Box 3)
    - Records 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Records 1973 (Box 3)
    - Records 1974-1982 (Box 3)
  - Marquette Chapter, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - Northwestern Chapter, 1956-1961 (Box 3)
  - Red Cedar Chapter
    - Constitution, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Records, 1970-1993, 23 folders (Box 3)
    - Records, 1990-1999 (include newsletters) (Box 3)
    - Newsletter, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
    - Spring Forays, 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - News, 1978-2007, 30 folders (Box 6)
  - Southeastern Chapter (Box 3)
    - Membership List, 1947-1957 (Box 3)
    - Records 1945-1949 (Box 3)
    - Records 1950-1959 (except 1951, 1952 1957) (Box 3)
    - Records 1960-1969 (except 1962), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Records 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Records 1985, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Southwestern Chapter, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Wild Life Chapter 1950 (Box 3)
- Activities
  The Activities series is arranged alphabetically. Included are records about the Big Trees Project, which documents Michigan's biggest trees and shrubs. Also documented in this series are Campouts, a weekend activity where the members participated in field trips and lectures. This series also presents documentation about legislation related to protection of flora sponsored by the Michigan Botanical Club.
  - Big Trees
    - 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960-1968 (except 1962-1963 1966) (Box 4)
    - 1970, 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1991 (Box 4)
  - Campouts
    - 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - 1951-1959 (except 1953 1958) (Box 4)
    - 1960-1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1970-1978 (except 1973 and 1977), 7 folders (Box 4)
    - 1981-1988 (except 1982 and 1985), 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Flowers Shows, March 26-April 3, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Food for Thought 1960-1962 (Box 4)
  - Horner Woods, 1964-1966, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Legislation
    - 1943 (Box 4)
    - 1954, 1956, 1959 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1969 (except 1963 and 1968) (Box 4)
    - 1970-1973 (except 1971) (Box 4)
    - 1980, 1983, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Botanist
    - 1961-1964 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Michigan State Parks Project, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Mushroom Booklet
    - 1962-1965, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1970, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Michigan United conservation Clubs
    - 1952, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960, 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1973-1979 (except 1977) (Box 4)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 4)
  - Natural Areas Council
    - History, 1958 Constitution, 1961 and General Information (Box 4)
    - 1949-1959 (except 1952), 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1960-1968 (except 1962-1964) (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Porcupine Mountains State Park
    - 1951, 1958, 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1961-1963 (Box 5)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Sleeping Bear, 1961-1965 (Box 5)
  - Waterloo Recreation Area
    - Survey Report, June 12, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Reports and Correspondence, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Reports and Correspondence, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Report, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
  - West Upper Maple River Watershed, December, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Wildflowers Protection (only one document is dated: 1975) (Box 5)
  - Winter Wildflowers Project
    - 1968 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is arranged alphabetically and contains Articles of Incorporation, Brochures and Insignias. It also includes a section of Newspaper Clippings and some Literature.
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1946, 1947, 1949 1975 (Box 5)
  - Asa Gray Bulletin, 1952 (Box 5)
  - MBC Blanks, undated (Box 5)
  - Brochures (Box 5)
  - Bulletins, undated
    - 1948, 1952-1954, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
    - 1960, 1963-1966 (except 1965) (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1941-1947 (Box 5)
  - Committee on Conservation and Education, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
  - Fish and Wildlife Service, 1978-1982 (except 1981) (Box 5)
  - Genevieve Gillette Speeches, January 23, 1966 May 5, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Gwen Frostic Records, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Insignias and Decals 1954, 1960, 1963-1964, 1968, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Literature
    - 1964-1969 (except 1968) (Box 5)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Scenic Sites Preliminary Inventory, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Mill Creek Metropolitan Park proposal, 1973 (Box 5)
  - National and Champion Trees in Michigan, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1941, 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1970-1979 (except 1973, 1977 and 1978) (Box 5)
    - 1982 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Scholarship School for Teachers, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Summary of Meetings, Reports and Activities, 1941-1958 (Box 5)